BEN BERKMAN

bjb433@nyu.edu | 814-321-4059 | 254 5th Ave, Apt. 4F, Brooklyn, NY, 11215 | https://github.com/benberkman

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Full-time MS in Data Science candidate at New York University's Center for Data Science. Three years of experience in data analytics consulting leading a major Department of Defense (DoD) data initiative. Significant experience in R programming, including package development, Shiny, and R Markdown. Currently pursuing a spring or summer 2021 data science internship or research opportunity. First year graduate course work includes Python programming, machine learning, deep learning, big data, probability and statistics, linear algebra, and optimization.

EDUCATION

New York University

September 2020 – May 2022 (intended graduation)

Center for Data Science – Master of Science in Data Science (in process)

Pennsylvania State University, Schreyer Honors College, University Park, PA

Graduated May 2017

College of the Liberal Arts—Bachelor of Science in Economics (Honors)

Honors Economics Thesis: Modeling Commute Time in New York City: A Spatial Econometric Approach

College of the Liberal Arts—Bachelor of Arts in French

GPA: 3.82/4.00

WORK EXPERIENCE

Technomics, Inc., Washington, D.C.

August 2017 - August 2020

Lead Analyst (previously: Senior Associate, Associate)

- Engineered automated data pipeline and validation processes in R to transform contractor accounting data into a government-standardized format. Accelerated process speed from previous iteration by more than 200 percent.
- Developed three R packages to streamline importing, standardizing, and analyzing new data format, the FlexFile. Distributed production-ready packages to three government program office customers. Published and presented FlexFiles: The Next Generation of Contractor Cost Data Reporting and The FlexFile Framework: Preparing for Powerful Analysis in R papers at 2019 and 2020 International Cost Estimating & Analysis Association (ICEAA) conferences, respectively, to introduce data format and packages.
- Led in-person trainings of up to 150 government analysts to demonstrate benefits of new data format. Curriculum included technical data skills in R, as well as overview of necessary policy and data requirements. Earned 2020 ICEAA Educator of the Year award for this effort.
- Directed a team of nine analysts in analyzing and validating cost and software data reports (CSDRs) submitted to the DoD for more than 70 Major Defense Acquisition Programs. Surpassed an aggressive metric monthly and maintained a low backlog of active reports. Communicated status to government client via in-person briefs and monthly written deliverable.
- Finalist: ICEAA Junior Analyst of the Year (2020).

AKRF, Inc., New York, New York

Summer 2015 and Summer 2016

Economics Group Summer Intern

- Created and analyzed data-rich GIS maps to provide spatial context for projects ranging from the new Tappan Zee Bridge to large-scale rezoning initiatives in Queens County, New York.
- Drafted economic impact statement for major frozen food company exploring relocation to upstate New York. Presented initial findings to project senior leadership, and developed portions of final report.
- Specialized analysis concentrations in indirect residential displacement and retail competition/capture rate studies of project areas.

Onward State, University Park, PA

August 2013 - August 2016

Athletics editor

- Led a team of 12 student-journalists covering more than 20 Penn State Division I sports for the largest student-run news organization in the country. Content reached more than 150,000 Twitter followers and amassed millions of pageviews.
- Authored more than 300 articles during three years on staff. Content ranged from comprehensive Penn State football features to a longform interview feature with the university president.

TOP SKILLS

Technical Skills:

Python • R • SQL • Git/GitHub • Mathematica • Stata • GIS (Arc and Q) • Business Intelligence tools (Tableau, Power BI)

Miscellaneous:

• Active Secret Security Clearance • Fluent in French • International Cost Estimating & Analysis Association (ICEAA) certified analyst (PCEA®)